A Guide to the Gertrude Stein Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8259
Gertrude Stein Collection 1922-1955
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8259
ca. 85 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 1963 Dec 17 ] 1966 May 11
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Essay, "Some Memories of Henri Matisse" by Alice B. Toklas, 1955 Feb 15; AMsS, 6 p.
    [Includes cover ALS, w/env to Editor of
    Yale Literary Magazine
    . ]
  - Essay, "The Work of Gertrude Stein" by Sherwood Anderson, TMs, 4 p.
    [Includes autograph corrections.]
  - Commentary of Gertrude Stein's Geography and Plays, AMs, 1 p.
- Letters
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Four Seas Publishing Company, Boston, TLS, 2 p.
    [Sends him manuscript of
    Geography and Plays
    , which is going to be her fifth book, for speedy publication; says she is willing to share the production cost and awaits his suggestions and proposition; says that Sherwood Anderson is to write the preface; gives him a list of prominent people who will advertise her in England and France, including G. H. Wells, Roger Fry, Israel Zwangwill, Logan Pearsall Smith, Jean Cocteau, Waldman George, and Valerie Larband. ]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, TLS, 4 p.
    [Says she is flattered that Brown likes the manuscript; tries to explain her method of work and how her style has developed since she wrote
    The Three Lives
    in 1905; feels fortunate to have Sherwood Anderson, a longtime admirer and student of her method, to explain her to the public; discusses the length, omissions, cost, and physical appearance of the book; suggests a royalty of 15 percent; says she will send a first payment of $1,000 toward the production.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1922 Jan 24; TLS, 3 p.
    [Includes autograph corrections; says she is happy with contract; asks for minor changes; talks about translation rights and the cost of translating; encloses $1,000 towards publishing cost; speaks about the book's physical shape and the preface by Sherwood Anderson; says she will send biographical sketch and her photo by Langdon Coburn as well as the one made from her portrait by Pablo Picasso; mentions that her "Portrait of Picasso," now being translated into French, will soon appear in Jean Cocteau's new magazine.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1922 Mar 2; TLS, 2 p.
    [Discusses his approval of the contract changes; suggests Curtis Brown to make arrangements for foreign publishing; mentions Sherwood Anderson's introduction of the book; tries to speed up the publishing as the book is already being talked about; mentions physical shape of book.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1922 May 11; TLS, 3 p.
    [Includes autograph corrections; returns corrected proofs and talks about them at length; mentions physical shape of book; requests a dummy of the cover; says she will send a list of names to send circulars to; mentions photographs of herself taken by Man Ray and includes one for publicity; mentions possibility of an English edition.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1922 Jul 10; TLS, 3 p.
    [Discusses corrected proofs and her definite ideas as to the looks of the book; sends list of people to whom advance notices should be sent; mentions sculpture of herself, which will be exhibited in America in the fall, being done by Jo Davidson; considers the sculpture good publicity for her book; sends second check of $2,000.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1922 Sep 9; ALS, 2 p.
    [Handwritten by Alice B. Toklas, signed by Stein; acknowledges receipt of a rough draft of the side papers; expresses definite ideas on how book should look; asks for a dummy as soon as possible.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1922 Oct 23; AL, 2 p.
    [Written by Alice B. Toklas for Stein; discusses
    encloses list of people to whom review copies should be sent; gives directions; mentions reviews in Canadian papers and in the Paris edition of the
    Chicago Tribune
    says there is interest in the book in Ireland. ]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1923 Feb 4; TLS, 1 p.
    [Compliments him and herself on the wonderful book they have produced; makes suggestions which might increase sales; requests that he send a copy to
    Life
    for review; promises more photographs of herself by Man Ray. ]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1923 Mar 6; TLS, 2 p.
    [Says she would like to know how many copies of
    have been sold and what has been done to advance the sale; hints at a future book; gives list of names she want copies sent to; mentions newspapers which are going to do a story on her and an article by Edna Kenton about the book; urges him to send copy to Don Marquis.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1923 May 10; TLS, 1 p.
    [Mentions book notices and reviews; scolds him for not writing to her, failing to inform about copies sold, and not sending a receipt for a check.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1923 May 14; TLS, 1 p.
    [Says that check and requested receipt have arrived; requests royalty statement; comments on book's success; says the interview by Jane Burr will appear in a large syndicate of newspapers; mentions article by Mina Loy about
    passes on flattering remarks about physical appearance of the book.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1923 Jul 10; TLS, 1 p.
    [Complains about not having received royalty statements for January, February, and March; mentions apparent success of book.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1923 Sep 15; TLS, 2 p.
    [Acknowledges receipt of statements and check covering all months up to June; encourages him to send quarterly statements from now on; says she is convinced that book sales will increase; mentions favorable newspaper clippings and that H. L. Mencken includes her in his list of the 10 dullest authors; says Mencken's statement leaves her undaunted.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1924 Jan 27; TLS, 2 p.
    [Acknowledges statement up to October; requests less tardiness with the next statement, due February 1; informs him that Ben W. Huebsch is bringing out a collection of her short stories, edited by Frances Newman; says she has given Huebsch permission to include "Miss Furr and Miss Skeene"; mentions reference to her work in a story that appeared in the September
    Cosmopolitan
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1924 Apr 23; TLS, 1 p.
    [Complains about errors and delays in his accounting; says she is glad about increased January sales; believes article in
    Atlantic Monthly
    will help with sales.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1924 Nov 22; TLS, 1 p.
    [Notes that all her books with the exception of
    are out of print; wonders if he saw the laudatory article in
    Vogue
    about
    by Edith Sitwell; says that Sitwell's article and Mina Loy's article have been mentioned in
    Punch
    reminds him to make sure the English agent has some copies; says statement and check are overdue.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1925 Mar 1; TLS, 2 p.
    [Asks him to supply new English agent with copies of
    says the book has come into demand after Edith Sitwell's piece; wants him to be sure that the book is available at the principal booksellers in Oxford and Cambridge; says that new interest in her work has arisen in England. ]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Mrs. Harry Atwood Coleman, Washington, D. C., 1925 Mar 22; TLS, 1 p.
    [Turns down invitation to the Author's Congress in Washington due to distance; understands that her books will be in the Book Fair; says she will instruct her publisher to be of help in any way he can.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Edmund R.] Brown, Boston, 1925 May 29; TLS, 2 p.
    [Discusses
    The Making of Americans
    and an overdue statement and royalty check.]
  - Gertrude Stein, France, to Mr. Pierre de Massot, Paris, 1930 May 14; APCS
    [Writes from the countryside; expresses pleasure on learning that he has written a preface for her book; comments on the weather; send greetings to his wife.]
  - Alice B. Toklas, Paris, to M. H. Brown, Boston, 1931 Apr 16; TLS, 1 p.
    [Mentions article in
    Axel's Castle
    on the work of Gertrude Stein; urges him to place an order for
    Lucy Church Amiably
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Sir Francis Rose, Paris, 1931 Nov 26; ANS, 1 p. w/env
    [Invites him to tea the following Sunday.]
  - Alice B. Toklas, Paris, to William Jackson, Ltd., London, 1934 Oct 11; TLS, 1 p.
    [Explains for Gertrude Stein that she has not written a book about Ernest Hemingway, but has discussed him in
    The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas
    informs him where the book was published.]
  - Alice B. Toklas, The Drake Hotel, Chicago, to Georgia Lingafelt, Chicago, 1934 Dec 1; TLS, 1 p.
    [Thanks her for "the delicate white violets" sent to Gertrude Stein; says that Stein hopes to find time to see Lingafelt upon her return to Chicago. ]
  - Alice B. Toklas, Bilignin, France, to Bruce Humphries, Inc., Boston, 1935 Jun 4; TLS, 1 p.
    [Asks for the long overdue statement of
    passes on Gertrude Stein's indignation over their ongoing tardiness.]
  - Bruce Humphries, Inc., Boston, to Alice B. Toklas, Bilignin, France, 1935 Jun 18; TL (carbon), 1 p.
    [Promises to send statement in early July; suggests that she study the contract in regard to her complaint.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Lt. Jean Deurel, Paris, 1945 May 11; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses 10,000 francs paid to her by Chabot and a check sent by Deurel from Fontaine.] (In French)
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Lt. Jean Deurel, Paris, 1945 Nov 15; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses arrangement with Chabot for
    Wars I Have Seen
    and
    Three Lives
    reports that her story on the Americans goes well.] (In French)
  - Alice B. Toklas, Paris, to William S. Byler, New Haven, CT, 1955 Jan 9; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses a piece she is supposed to write for
    The Yale Literary Magazine
    to honor Henri Matisse; explains how the rift between Gertrude Stein and Matisse came about; promises a contribution within a fortnight.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belignin par Belley, to Pierre de Massot, Paris, [ca. 1930]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Expresses delight about the preface he has done for
    Dix Portraits
    loves his use of quotations; looks forward to the
    Bull-Dog
    says she would like to own a lot of his writings; refers to her dog "Basket"; invites him and his wife Robbie to spend a few days with them in Bilignin. ]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belignin par Belley, to Pierre de Massot, Paris, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Invites him and [Robbie] to visit; speaks about the delightful countryside, the weather, her work.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belignin par Belley, to Pierre de Massot, Paris, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says she greatly enjoyed his book; enjoys "actualities of 1358"; hopes to meet him in Paris next winter.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belignin par Belley, to Pierre de Massot, [ Paris], n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Compliments him on his beautiful writing, especially [
    Bull Dog
    ]; expresses interest in his historical writings; hopes he and Mrs. Robertson will visit her.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belignin par Belley, to Pierre de Massot, Paris, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Mentions pieces he has written; renews invitation to Bilignin; mentions "Basket."]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belignin par Belley, to Pierre de Massot, Paris, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says she has been doing interesting work and is anxious to share her ideas with him in September.]
  - Gertrude Stein, New York, to [ Potter Palmer], [ Chicago], [1934]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for telegram and all he did for her; talks about an upcoming broadcasting about her lectures and books.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingninpar Belley, to Virgil Thomson, Honfleur, Calvados, n. d.; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Thanks him for the "marked" copy; approves of the changes he has made; says she will send a presentation copy.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingninpar Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Invites him to visit; says she is busy reading proof; describes her country place as crude, but lovely; suggests a longer visit for later.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingninpar Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [Says her arm is on the mend; invites him to visit; suggests he keep producing paintings and not worry about gallery politics; describes the pleasure his pictures have given a local French family who saw them at her home.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, Paris, n. d.; ALS, 6 p.
    [Comments on his paintings; gives business advice; suggests a gallery which will put his work in a large exhibition hall; warns him not to raise his prices at this time; singles out 2 of his paintings, "the two old heads" and "the grey nude against the greenish background" as praiseworthy.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, [Mougins], France, 1935; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says that there is a great deal in his painting that she does not like, but she likes him, is proud of him, and has faith in him; thinks that, if he persist, he will eventually be what her letter-head, which says "Rose is a rose.. .," suggests.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, [ Paris], n. d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [Refuses to give one of his pictures to a gallery in exchange for another one to be chosen by the gallery; says that she bought 3 pictures from a previous show to prove her continued support, not because she was impressed.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to William Buehler Seabrook, n. d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [Expresses delight with [
    The Magic Island
    ]; finds him "simple and gay and wonderful"; walks endlessly; talks and listens to the peasants; says she is happy about all he says about her.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to William Buehler Seabrook, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says she is pleased to have heard from him; asks him to send the book; reports on their planting potatoes, American corn and American squash; hopes to meet him again soon.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses letter from Rose, which she showed to Bernard Fay, and a letter by "Waldemar"; says she met Waldemar at the gallery where Rose's pictures are on exhibit and he was impressed; advises him to let Waldermar write an article on the paintings; reports on her difficult financial situation.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas
    , photos to be used in the book and for publicity; asks about the date of his visit so they can arrange a party; says that the room has been painted and whitewashed and his paintings look lovely in it; remembers Curley, his dog.] (on "Rose is a rose. ." stationary)
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 3 p.
    [Invites him for a weekend; suggests that he stop at his place en route to see how the workmen are doing and to go back there Monday to keep an eye on everything.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [Advises him to exhibit 3 paintings; suggest medicinal baths for an ailing arm; relates comments on his art by her local friends, both cultivated and not; talks about their dogs.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Cernchild], New York, [1935]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Reminisces about America; says Colette and her new husband will go to New York on the Normandie's maiden voyage and will stay at the Waldorf, carrying a letter from Stein to [Cernchild]; assures him that he and Colette will like each other.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Sir Frances Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for Christmas gift of Rembrandt drawings, which she greatly admires; mentions "Basket's" Christmas present and Rose's dogs.] (on "Rose is a rose. ." stationary)
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Reports on arrival in the country from Paris; comments on the weather, Basket's reactions to the move, etc.; looks forward to her 2 new pictures; writes about the changes she has made in hanging his pictures.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Talks about her and Alice B. Toklas' visit to the Roses and about Basket who cannot come along due to skin problems; promises that Basket will be beautiful again in the fall, to have his portrait painted.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, [ca. 1942-42]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Gives him advice on galleries; advises him not to send pictures to her as the person who used to frame the pictures is ill and she does not have anybody trustworthy to crate them to be sent back; expresses pleasure about a drawing.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Speaks about a pleasant visit with him, how they get to know each other better every time; suggests they visit St. Remy together; knows a Chinese landscape in miniature there she wants him to paint; discusses changes in her household due to a change of landlords.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses a visit from Rose put off by his illness and his dog Curley; mentions his painting "the little seven year old" which pleases her.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Complains about a recently received picture; understands why the London show has been a disappointment; remembers Rose telling her that an artist has to paint bad pictures; says she is afraid he lets it turn into a habit and that she will not sponsor his New York show if his work does not improve; warns him that he is no longer young and he has to fulfill his youthful promise.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Francis Rose, [1935]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for a picture; tells him that she likes the St. Remy as much as ever; comments on the light; tells him that she believes in him as painter.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Wonders about his well being; offers to help him in Paris if necessary; reasures him of her interest in him.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for picture.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says she has found a purchaser if he has a picture to sell at 300 or 400 francs; discusses dogs.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Appreciates pictures he sent her which justify her faith in him; loves one painting especially, the "new one"; talks about the quality of light in it, inner and outer light.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses the placement of his work in American galleries to get the American public acquainted with him; says she will do the introduction in a catalogue for him; asks him to send her a copy of the London show catalogue.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Sir Francis Rose, [1933]; ALS, 4 p.
    [Says she has found a London agent, [Abdy], and gotten him interested in Rose's work; says [Abdy] would be willing to put together a London show of paintings and drawings for Rose, provided Rose takes care of letter writing, appearances, etc.; states that the agents think the recent publicity Rose got from
    would be of help.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, ca. 1936; ALS, 4 p.
    [Talks about his pictures; advises him to stick with Paris art dealer Pierre Colle who is the only dealer selling pictures at the moment; says she has gotten an important English collector interested in his work and that she will send Rose to London in the fall; mentions that Lord Berner is doing the music and the decor for one of her plays to be performed in the fall.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS
    [Discusses a landscape he wants; suggests the cascade he did at Bilignin, one of her favorite pictures; expresses pleasure with the photos of the church "Curley" sent her; invites him to dinner on the 25th.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Comments on ill health; mentions pleasure she got out of a number of his pictures.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Sir Francis Rose, ca. 1932; ANS, 2 p.
    [Tells him that a letter the agent Sir Robert Abdy sent him has been returned; urges him to got to post office, see what is the matter; states that the agent want to talk to Rose; sends Christmas and New Year's wishes.] (on "Rose is a rose.. ." stationary)
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to Sir Francis Rose, [1934]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses pictures he sent; describes the ones he likes; says she is afraid she will miss the Chicago show because they will not arrive there before the 24th of March, by which time the show may be over.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Belingnin par Belley, to [ Potter Palmer], Chicago, [1934]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses his possible trip to France that year, her upcoming lectures at Columbia University; thanks him for all he and [Harriet ?] have done for her.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to [Dr. Johnston], n. d.; ANS, 2 p.
    [Tells him that "
    On Indian Bay
    , " in which he figures, is published in the
    Reviewer
    hopes he likes it.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Pierre de Massot, Paris, [ca. 1933]; ANS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses a meeting with him; says she would like him to do the introduction to the "Potraits"; says she is pleased that their books came out at the same time.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Pierre de Massot, Paris, n. d.; ANS, 2 p.
    [Hopes he is not ill; expects him at tea-time Sunday; says Bernard [Fay] will come also.]
  - Gertrude Stein, Paris, to Pierre de Massot, Paris, n. d.; ANS, 2 p.
    [Says she is pleased to have heard from him; looks forward to seeing him again.]
- Photographs
  - Magazine photo of Gertrude Stein, side view, 1937 Dec 5; Photo
  - Newspaper photo of Gertrude Stein, seated, 1946 Jul 28; Photo
  - Newspaper cut of Gertrude Stein, side view, n. d.; Photo
  - Magazine photo of Gertrude Stein, head and shoulders, Photo
  - Photo of a portrait by Pablo Picasso of Gertrude Stein, seated, n. d.; Photo
- Miscellaneous
  - Gertrude Stein for publication of Geography and Plays, 1922 Jan 26; Contract
    [Signed.]
  - Gertrude Stein for publication of Geography and Plays, [1930]; Contract
  - Clipping about Gertrude Stein, [1939]; Clipping
    [Includes envelope addressed to Georgia Lingafelt. ]